Guide to the Thomas Lindsey Blayney papers, 1893-2004 MS 064
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Thomas Lindsey Blayney papers
1893-2004
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Blayney, Thomas Lindsey
MS 064
17 Linear Feet (23 boxes)
Papers of Thomas Lindsey Blayney, a founding member of the faculty of Rice Institute (now University) and Professor of German there from 1912- 1924; materials include records of his military service during World War I (1917-1919), and later appointments as president of Texas State Women's College (1924-26) and dean of Carleton College (1926-46); also included are family memoirs, correspondence, photographs, news clippings, and memorabilia.
Biographical Note
Thomas Lindsey Blayney was born in Lebanon, Kentucky, on December 3, 1874. He spent his early childhood in Albany, New York, and after the death of his mother in 1881 moved with his father and younger brother to Frankfort, Kentucky, where his father served as a Presbyterian minister. Blayney graduated from Centre College in Danville, Kentucky, in 1894, and went on to Europe for graduate studies, where he studied philology and comparative literature at Heidelberg University and received M.A. and Ph.D. degrees with honor in 1904.
In 1912 he became one of the founding faculty members of the newly-established Rice Institute in Houston, Texas (later Rice University). During his twelve years on the faculty there (1912-1924), Blayney was also much involved in the expanding civic and cultural life of Houston, particularly in the establishment of what was to become Houston's Museum of Fine Arts, and in activities as a participant and lecturer in various community organizations. He was among the first faculty members at Rice to volunteer for military service during World War I and served from 1917 to 1919, during which time he was awarded the French Croix de Guerre among other honors. He returned to Rice after the war but left in 1924 to become president of Texas State Women's College.
In 1926 he went on to become dean of Carleton College in Northfield, Minnesota, serving in this capacity until his retirement in 1946. His first wife, Gertrude South Blayney, died in 1945; they had two sons, James M. Blayney and Lindsey Blayney, Jr. He later married Ida Walz, and after his retirement moved to Marine-on-St.-Croix, Minnesota, where he died March 13, 1971.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas Lindsey Blayney Papers, dating from 1893 to 2004, include an autobiographical letter written by Blayney to his sons, from which much information may be obtained about Blayney's academic and community activities and his military service during World War I. Of special interest also are photographs of Blayney during his service in World War I, the Croix de Guerre medal awarded to him by the French, and the numerous newspaper clippings concerning his academic activities as a faculty member at the Rice Institute (1912-1924) and his role in the expanding cultural life of Houston during this period.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
The Thomas Lindsey Blayney Papers were a gift from David Blayney, received February 6 and March 30, 2004. Deanna Costanzo made a subsequent gift received in June 2009.
General
Portions of this collection are available online at: https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/26634
Related Material
See also other early Rice Institute material, including the campus newspaper and yearbook (the Rice Thresher and Rice Campanile, respectively), photographs, and alumni scrapbooks.
Index Terms
Subjects
Military; Education; World War (1914-1918); World War (1939-1945); Universities and colleges
Document Types
biographies (documents); memorabilia; photographs; genealogies (histories); corrrespondence; manuscripts (document genre); clippings (information artifacts); black-and-white photographs; obituaries
Subjects (Corporations)
American Legion; Houston Art League; Carleton College (Northfield, Minn.); Rice University
- Series I: Biographical Materials, 46366
  - "The Blayney and Allied Families," compiled by Chester Oliver Blayney; Columbus, Ohio, 46371 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Genealogical Material, 46370 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Genealogical Material, 46369 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Material, 46368 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Autobiographical Letter to his sons, February, 10, 1959, 46367 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1893-1974, 46301
  - Correspondence, Military, 46360
    - American Legion, 1910 - 1921, 46365 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - U.S. War Department, 1920s, 46364 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Application for Retirement Benefits; Office of Veterans Affairs, 46363 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Col. Lucien Beckner, 1961 - 1962, 46362 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - First Officers Training Camp Association, 1970, 46361 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Personal, 46344
    - 1920 - 1927, 46359 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Lac La Croix, 1930s - 1940s, 46358 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Gertrude Blayney (wife), illness and death, 1945, 46357 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1959 and Undated, 46356 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1945 (wife Gertrude's death and to his son at college), 46355 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poetry, 1960s, 46354 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1960s, 46353 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Christmas Cards, 1960s - 1970s, 46352 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Christmas Inscriptions, 1965, 46351 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1970 and Undated, 46350 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Final Illness, 1971, 46349 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Ida Walz Blayney, Issue of Carleton Alumni Publication, Lindsey Blayney: A Strong Man," 1972, 46348 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Death, Funeral, Letters from Ida Blayney, 1970s, 46347 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Operation Identification" for Personal Possessions, 1974, 46346 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Invitations and Clubs, 46345 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Education and Presentations, 46327
    - Undated, 46343 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Committee on the Teaching of the History of Art in Colleges, 1910-1912 and Undated, 46342 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Publication of Art History Book with G.P. Putnam Sons, 1910, 46341 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1920s RE: Presidents and Secretaries Conference, Portland, Oregon, 46340 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1922 Defense of Thesis, 46339 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Kuno Franke Volume, 1924 - 1925, 46338 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Texas Superintendent Position, 1926, 46337 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Royal Geographic Society, 1931-1932, 46336 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Radio Forum; St. Olaf Public Addresses by Dean Blayney, 1939 - 1940, 46335 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Speeches and Presentations, 1938, 46334 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Houston Art League, Letters to Judge Garwood, 1940s, 46333 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1940 - 1944, 46332 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Contents of Leather Binder 1960s, 46331 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Presentation to Lyndon Baines Johnson (Leather Binder), 46330 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Presentation to Mrs. Lyndon "Lady Bird" Johnson (Leather Binder), 46329 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1965 - 1972, 46328 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, Carleton College, 46308
    - Carleton College, 1920 - 1927, 46326 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Teachers' Insurance and Annuity Association, 1927 - 1940, 46325 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1927 - 1928, 46324 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1928 - 1929, 46323 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1929 - 1930, 46322 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1930 - 1931, 46321 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1931 - 1932, 46320 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1932 - 1933, 46319 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1933 - 1934, 46318 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1934 - 1935, 46317 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1935 - 1936, 46316 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1936 - 1937, 46315 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1937 - 1938, 46314 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1938 - 1939, 46313 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - President Donald J. Cowling, Carleton College, 1940 - 1941, 46312 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Frank Shigemura, 1940s, 46311 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Report on the Year 1945 - 1946 at Carleton College [Ida Walz Kubitz], 46310 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Army Specialized Training Program (ASTP), 1940s, 46309 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, Postcards from Album "Grusse aus der Ferne", 46302
    - Postcards, 1893, Undated, 46307 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Postcards, 1897, 46306 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Postcards, 1898, 1899, 46305 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Postcards, 1901, 1902, 46304 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Postcards, 1903-1905; 1913-1914, 46303 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Series III: Writings, 46272
  - Writings, Education, 46291
    - Education, Undated, 46300 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "The Renascence [sic] of the Liberal Art College," 1912; "The Liberal Arts College and the New South," 1912, 46299 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "History of Art as a College Discipline," 1910; "Our Colleges and Literary Disciplines," 1924; "Modern Language as Cultural College Discipline," 1911, 46298 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Draft of Transcript "Why Teach?" Undated, 46297 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Draft of "American Ideals vs. American Education," Undated, 46296 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "American Ideals and Education," Undated, 46295 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "American Ideals and Traditions," Published 1922 in The North American Review, 46294 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Frank Shigemura, 1945, 46293 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Programs from Speeches Given by Blayney, 46292 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Writings, 46273
    - Poetry and Prose (Including "A Nation Awaits," "A Noble Edifice," "A Star of Hope," "A Strange Story," "An Enlightened Land," "Belongingness," and "Moon of St. Croix"), 46290 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Speeches and Notes, 1920s - 1940s, 46289 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Typescript: The German Spirit, I - III, 46288 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Typescript: The German Spirit, IV - VII, 46287 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Typescript: The German Spirit, VIII, 46286 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Typescript: The German Spirit, IX, 46285 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Typescript: The German Spirit, X, 46284 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Typescript: The German Spirit, XI, 46283 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "Every Man Rises: The Temple of the Nation's Soul," 1920s, 46282 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Blayney's National Geographic article "A Journey in Morocco: 'The Land of the Moors'", 46281 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - "Our Administration of the Philippine Islands", 46280 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - "Chinese Art and Ideals," Undated, 46279 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - "The Art of Japan," Undated, 46278 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - "Impressions of Indian Art and Idealism," Undated, 46277 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Typescript: Synopses of Tosca, Lohengrin, and Tannhauser, 46276 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Unidentified, Undated, 46275 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Programs from Presentations by Blayney, 46274 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Series IV: Newspaper Clippings and Obituaries, 46254
  - Newspaper Clippings, 46267
    - 1910 - 1920s, 46271 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1910 - 1919, 46270 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 1920 - 1929, 46269 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 1920 - 1929, 46268 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Obituaries, 46255
    - Sir Aukland Geddes, British Ambassador, at Rice Institute following his address to the students, May 12, 1921, 46266 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Tribute in Texas Outlook, 1923, 46265 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1930 - 1939, 46264 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1940 - 1949, 46263 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1950 - 1959, 46262 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1960 - 1969, 46261 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1970 - 1979, 46260 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Undated, 46259 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - "Quotable", 46258 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Comments from School, 46257 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Funeral/Memorial Book, 46256 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Series V: Photographs, 46217
  - Family, Friends, and School, 46244
    - Blayney Portraits and Solo Images, 46253 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Blayney at Boy's Academy in Kentucky, 46252 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Blayney with Wife; Wife Portraits and Solo Images, 46251 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Family Photographs, 46250 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Family and Friends, 46249 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Homes, Including: Danville and Northfield, 46248 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Outdoor Activities: Canoeing, Camping, Fishing, 46247 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Carleton College, 46246 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Rice, Houston Museum, "Rice - Lovett," and "Our Lounge", 46245 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - World War I, World War II, Military Service, 46238
    - World War I and World War II, 46243 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Paris, including Peace Conference, 46242 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - World War I Military Service, 46241 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Blayney with his Unit, 46240 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Europe: Germany, Paris; World War I Era, 46239 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Travel - United States, Canada, Europe, 46229
    - Travel, United States, 46237 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Travel, Canada, 46236 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Travel, Unidentified "Overseas", 46235 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Travel, Various: Algeria, Rome, Greece, Italy, Naples, Morocco, Africa, 46234 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Travel, Various: Switzerland, Italy, Spain, Portugal, Germany, Serbia, 46233 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Travel, England and Holland; KAHN Fellowship, 46232 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Travel, Heidelberg, Germany, 46231 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Travel, India, 46230 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Travel and Extras, 46218
    - Travel, Asia, 46228 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Travel, Japan and China, 46227 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Travel, Macedonia, 46226 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Travel, Philippines, 46225 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Travel, Philippines, 46224 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified People, Photo Cards, and Scenery, 46223 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Slides: Illuminated Manuscripts and "Home" (Lac La Croix?), 1962 - 1963; 1965, 46222 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Negatives, 46221 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Copies of Photos, 46220 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Photocopies of Photos with Information, 46219 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Memorabilia and Oversize, 46186
  - Wooden Case with Cavalry Horse Tack, 46216 (Box 11)
  - Military Regalia: Hats (2), 46215 (Box 12)
  - Military Regalia, Cavalry Uniform Jacket, tan (stored separately from collection; see separation sheet), 46214 (Box 13)
  - Military Regalia, Cavalry Uniform Jacket, olive, 46213 (Box 14)
  - Military Regalia: Hats (2); Academic Regalia: Mortarboards (2), 46212 (Box 15)
    - Assorted Personal Memorabilia and Oversized Items, 46187
      - Carleton College Brochure, 46204 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Honorarium from the Texas State College for Women, 46203 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Booklet, Goethe, 46202 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Postcards and Cards, 46201 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - Blayney Coat of Arms, Notepaper, Military Officer Cards, 46200 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Croix de Guerre Medal; Letter Explaining Provenance, 46199 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - Assorted Keepsakes, 46198 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - Thomas Flaxman Scholarship honoring Dr. Blayney, 46197 (Box 23, Folder 8)
      - Scroll of Appreciation written by Dr. Blayney after Rice University's Semi-centennial Celebration, 1962, 46196 (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - Personal Stationery, 46195 (Box 23, Folder 10)
      - Photographs: Lindsey Blayney Jr. and Family, 46194 (Box 23, Folder 11)
      - Photographs: Family Photos and Portraits, 46193 (Box 23, Folder 12)
      - Photographs: Camping, Canoeing, Fishing, 46192 (Box 23, Folder 13)
      - Photographs: Travel, 46191 (Box 23, Folder 14)
      - Photographs: Military Service, 46190 (Box 23, Folder 15)
      - Photographs: Academia, 46189 (Box 23, Folder 16)
      - Documents: Blayney Honorarium, Frank Shigemura Memorial, 46188 (Box 23, Folder 17)
  - Honorarium (clock, cup), 46211 (Box 16)
  - Academic Memorabilia: Stoles (3), 46210 (Box 17)
  - Academic and Personal Memorabilia: Yearbook, Briefcase, Nameplate, Wallet, 46209 (Box 18)
  - Personal Memorabilia: Top Hat, 46208 (Box 19)
  - Personal Memorabilia: Hats (2), 46207 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbooks with Postcards (2), 46206 (Box 21)
  - Blue banners with Ivory Fringe (6), 46205 (Box 22)
  - Memorabilia: Croix de Guerre Medal, 2000-04 (Box 23)
  - Carleton College Brochure (Box 23, Envelope 1)
  - Academic Memorabilia: Honorarium from the Texas State College for Women (Box 23, Envelope 2)
  - Booklet, Goethe, 1949 (Box 23, Envelope 3)
  - Postcards, Cards, 1897- (Box 23, Envelope 4)
  - Blayney Coat of Arms and notepaper; Blayney military officer's cards (Box 23, Envelope 5)
  - Memorabilia: Letter explaining Croix de Guerre Medal, 1974-11-05 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Misc. Keepsakes (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Academic Memorabilia: Thomas Flaxman Scholarship honoring Dr. Lindsey Blayney, 1962 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Academic Memorabilia: Scroll of Appreciation written by Dr. Lindsey Blayney after Rice University semi-centennial celebration, 1962 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Personal Memorabilia: Personal stationery (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Oversize Photographs
    - Lindsey Blayney, Jr, Jr. Jr., and Dorothy, ca.1920-1940 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Family Photos and Portraits, 1913- (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Camping, Canoeing, and Fishing (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Travel (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Military Service (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - Academia (Box 23, Folder 16)
    - Rice Honorarium - Frank Shigemura Memorial (Box 23, Folder 17)